Guide to the Michael Glaser papers, 1969-2020 MS2256
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Michael Glaser papers
1969-2020
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Glaser, Michael S.
MS2256
6.25 Linear Feet
This collection contains records of the St. Mary's Literary Festival and other literary materials produced and gathered by Michael Glaser (1943-) from 1969-2007. Dr. Michael Glaser was the co-founder and director of the festival, and professor of English at St. Mary's College of Maryland from 1970-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Some files are restricted because social security numbers were found on some documents. Redacted copies were made, and a general note on separated items is included at each file level. The originals are in Box R1.
Biographical note
Michael S. Glaser (1943-), poet laureate of Maryland, served as both an administrator and a professor at St. Mary's College of Maryland for more than 35 years. Dr. Glaser was born in Chicago, Illinois in 1943 and received his B.A. from Denison University and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Kent State University. He began teaching at St. Mary's in 1970. While at St. Mary's, he co-founded and directed the bi-annual Literary Festival and the annual Voices reading series. Dr. Glaser has published more than 500 poems and three poetry collections. He is a recipient of the Homer Dodge Endowed Award for Excellence in Teaching, and the Columbia Merit Award from the Poetry Committee of the Greater Washington, D.C. area.
Dr. Glaser lives in St. Mary's City with his wife. He is the proud father of five grown children and six grandchildren.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains event planning records, poems, literary manuscripts, correspondence, and newspaper clippings. The material dates from 1969-2007. These are the papers of Michael Glaser during his time as professor at St. Mary's College of Maryland. Dr. Glaser served as director of the St. Mary's Literary Festival, originally known as the Festival of Poets and Poetry, and the material in the collection primarily relates to the organization and products of the Festival. There is also material related to Lucille Clifton, Dr. Glaser's friend, colleague, and fellow poet.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael Glaser, 2009 (2009.002) and 2020 (2020.032)
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: St. Mary's literary events and courses, Literary manuscripts and publications, and Correspondence and newspaper clippings.
Separated Materials
The 2020.032 donation included two publications: Conversations with Lucille, a second Voices memorial tribute to Lucille Clifton edited by Michael Glaser and now is the thing to praise by Dolores Kendrick. Those publications were removed from the collection and cataloged as part of the Special Collections book collection.
Literary Festival; English literature; Correspondence; Newspapers; Poetry; Literature; Poetry -- Workshops; St. Mary's College of Maryland
- St. Mary's College of Maryland literary events and courses, 1969-2005, 2020; Series 1; 4 Linear Feet 8 document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to St. Mary's College of Maryland literary events and academic courses organized or taught by Michael Glaser from 1969-2005. The materials include CDs of the SMCM Literary Festival.
  Arrangement
  The first part of this series (Boxes 1-5) is arranged chrologically, preserving the folders' original order. The second part of the series (Boxes 6-8) is arranged alphabetically by folder title. The subject matter may overlap between the folders in these two arrangements.
  - MSG Senate Speeches Reports, 1975-1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Faculty, 1974; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - '79 Festival, 1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Festival 1980, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Festival 1981, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - News Release Letterheads, 1981-1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Festival 1982, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Workshop 1983, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - '83 Festival Appreciations, 1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Festival 1979-1983, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CM & RS Course & SMCM Equivalent, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oxford-List of Past Students, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dr. John Feneley, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oxford 1984 Correspondence, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports to the Dean, 1986-1988; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oxford Correspondence, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 84 Festival, 1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Festival 1985, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1985-86 Readings, 1985-1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Festival 1986, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Festival 1987, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 87-88 Reading Series, 1987-1988; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Festival 1988, Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Festival 88, 1988; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1988 Masters Summer Poetry Writing Workshop, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Festival 1989, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    General
    Original title: "Heinick's Song"
  - 1989 Festival, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1990 Festival, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Festival-1990, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1991 Festival, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1992 Festival, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 92 Intensive Poetry Writing Workshop, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Weekend II-92, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Weekend I and II Poem, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 92 Weekend I Poets, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 92-95 Grants, 1992-1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1993 Festival of P & P, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Program I '93, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Program II '93, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mailings (93) Packets- To Poets, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fiction Workshop, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 93 Poetry Weekend I, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 93 Writer's Community Retreat, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1994- Intensive Poetry Writing Workshop, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1994 Festival, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Poetry/Poetry Fiction Logos, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Festival/Class Notes, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Festival-Michael Glaser, 1994-2002; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 95 Fest Weekends I & II, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Glaser's Eschatological Laundry List, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Nifty Quotes File, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Weekend II, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Poets Contracts & Bio, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Weekend I, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Retreat, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Given to Poetry Workshop, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - IPW Syllabus 1995, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Festival-1995, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fiction 95, 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Fiction Workshop 1995, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Festival-Michael Glaser (Workshop), 1995; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Creative Writing Classes, 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Festival '96, 1996; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Retreat 1996, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Fiction '96, 1996; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 96 Poetry Workshop, 1996; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Weekend II 1996, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Weekend I 1996, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Workshop Teaching Folder, 1996; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 96-99 Grants, 1996-1999; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 97 Bios & Pics, 1997; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Poetry Workshop, 1997; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1997 Literary Festival, Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Weekend II, 1997; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Weekend I, 1997; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Poetry-Glaser, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Humanities Council-Grant Application, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Retreat 98, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 98 Poetry Workshop, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 98 Fiction Workshop, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Masters-98, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 98 Festival, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Map to College/Directions DC/Balt, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Keep off signs, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Writer Letter, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 98-Dear WRiter Letter 1&2, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Weekend Confirm, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - 98-Reservation Form, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Dear Friend '98, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Packets, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - 98 Weekend Reservation Form, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - 98-Dear Writer Letter, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Bios & Poems-Weekend II, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 98 Weekend II, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Weekend II packets, 1999; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Bios & Poems-Weekend I, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 98 Weekend I, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Sr. Reading, 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Copies for letters for app., 1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - 1999 Lecture Proposal: Toni Morrison, Series 1 (Box R1, Folder 1, Box 4, Folder 32)
    Separated item(s)
    A portion of the contents of the folder have been redacted. Original items are closed for research.
  - 1999 Literary Festival, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1999 Literary Festival Information, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - SMCM Transcriptions of Poetry Festival, 1999; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 2000 Summer Writers' Workshops, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Packet 2000, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Celebration 2000, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 2000-2001 Events, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 2002 Intensive Poetry Writing Workshop, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Weekend I Poems 2002, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Michael Glaser Nominations, 2003; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 2004 Poetry Retreat, Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - College literary publications, 1969-1997; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cooke miscellaneous letterhead, letters, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cooke past programs, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - E. Cooke Festival 1990, Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Past Cooke grants, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - E. Cooke (general), 1981-1992; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Pre-1985 Cooke guest list, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Cooke-1992, Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Ebenezer Cooke Poetry Festival, undated; Series 1 (Box R1, Folder 2, Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1994 Cooke SMAC application, Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Invite to 94 Cooke, 1994; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Festival information, 1987-1991; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Festival plans, 1985-1991; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Festival, 1984-1993; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Glaser, Michael- teaching, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Glaser, Michael- other, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Letters/supplementary materials, 1987-1993; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Library of Congress- Michael Glaser, undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Literary events, undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Literary events, 1994-2003; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Literary Festival information, correspondence, undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Literary Festival information, 1993-2004; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Literary Festival poems and fiction, undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Literary Festival poems and fiction, 1997-2000; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Literary Festival Weekend I & II information and poems, undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Literary Festival: Writers Workshops & Retreats, 1996-2000; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Literary Festival, 1982-1995; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Poems and fiction from St. Mary's classes and events, 1983-1997; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Poetry events, St. Mary's College, 2005, 2020, undated; MS2256 Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Poetry reading flyers, 1979-2003; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Sample packets, 1994-1998; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - VOICES reading series, 1992-2003; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - VOICES, 1997-2002; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Women-in-Poetry, 1997-2005; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - '95 & '96 SMCM Lit. Festival (cont.) copy 1, 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 1)
  - '96 & '97 SMCM Lit Festival copy 1, 1996-1997; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 2)
  - '97 SMCM Lit Festival (cont.) copy 1, 1997; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 3)
  - 1998 SMCM Lit Festival copy 1, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 4)
  - '98 & '99 SMCM Lit Festival copy 1, 1998-1999; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 5)
  - 2002 SMCM Workshop and Festival copy 1, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 6)
  - 2004 SMCM Poetry Festival copy 1, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 7)
  - '95 and '96 SMCM Lit. Festival (cont.) copy 2, 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 8)
  - '96 and '97 Lit Festival SMCM copy 2, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 9)
  - '97 SMCM Lit. Festival (cont.) copy 2, 1997; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 10)
  - 1998 SMCM Lit. Festival copy 2, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 11)
  - '98 and '99 SMCM Lit. Festival copy 2, 1998-1999; Series 1 (Box 12, Item 12)
  - 2002 SMCM Workshop and Lit. Festival copy 2, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 13)
  - 2004 SMCM Poetry Festival copy 2, Series 1 (Box 12, Item 14)
- Literary manuscripts and publications, 1971-2016; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains literary manuscripts and publications not directly related to St. Mary's College of Maryland from 1971-2016. The materials include poems written by Michael Glaser and Roland Flint, a play by Grace Cavalieri, and information on the Millenial Project (Weavings 2000). The series also includes CDs, audiocassettes, and a videotape.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Acceptance letters, 1998-2000; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bio notes Millenial Project, 1999; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Book: In honor of Michael Glaser and Brian Ganz, 2007; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Essays, 1998; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Maryland magazine- Spring 1981, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Michael Glaser publicity, 2004-2016; MS2256 Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Pinecrest Rest Haven by Grace Cavalieri, 1999; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Poems, undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Poetry anthology, 1979; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Poetry books, 1971-1988; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Poetry event fliers, 1982-2005; MS2256 Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Roland Flint publication material, 1980-1995; MS2256 Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Shewski's Ladder by Katharine Zadravec, 1980; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Washington writers: signed manuscript and book later published, 1984; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Washington Review, 2000; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Weavings & Musings project information, 2001; Series 2 (Box R1, Folder 3, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Weavings, 2001; Series 2 (Box R1, Folder 4, Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Michael's File- Weavings 2000, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Weavings 2000 press release, Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Workshop designs, undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 31 Arlington Poets CD, 2004; Series 2 (Box 12, Item 15)
  - Natives, Tourists & Other Mysteries: Emerging Washington Poets audiocassettes, 1985; Series 2 (Box 12, Cassette 16)
  - Ann Darr: High Dark audiocassette, 1978; Series 2 (Box 12, Cassette 17)
  - HoCoPoLitSo present Garrison Keillor Roland Flint audiocassette, 1994; Series 2 (Box 12, Cassette 18)
  - A Poetry Reading: Maura Eichner, S.S.N.D. videotape, 1990; Series 2 (Box 12, Videocassette 19)
- Correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1977-2006; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains correspondence and newspaper clippings from 1977-2006. Items include Michael Glaser's correspondence, Glaser's letters answering Lucille Clifton's mail, letters nominating Glaser for awards, newspaper clippings about Glaser, and newspaper clippings about Clifton.
  - Correspondence/permissions, 1989-2000; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Clifton, Lucille- magazine articles about, 1999; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Clifton, Lucille- newspaper clippings, 1989-1993; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Lucille, 1999; Series 3 (Box R1, Folder 5, Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Articles on Clifton, 1994-2001; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Glaser, Michael- correspondence, 1990-2006; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Glaser, Michael- newspaper clippings, 1989-2001; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings- general, 1977-2000; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)